<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Source material for the Corpus of Historical Mapudungun (CHM)</title>
    <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Source material for the Corpus of Historical Mapudungun (CHM)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2021 Benjamín Molineaux</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1930 16:45:54 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Pascual Coña (Ernesto Wilhelm de Moesbach)</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/pc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1930 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/pc/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
Prologue, editing and notes by Dr. Rudolf Lenz
Full title: &amp;ldquo;Vida y costumbres de los indígenas araucanos de la segunda mitad del Siglo XIX&amp;rdquo;
Background
The text is the autobiography of Chief (Lonco) Pascual Coña, as related to the Capuchin priest Ernst Wilhelm Moesbach. By the time these memories were compiled (mid-1920s), Coña was an older man, in his 70s or 80s, so much of the content relates to the second half of the 19th century.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Félix de Augusta: Kiñewén Amuaiyu: Vade Mecum!</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/vademecum/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1925 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/vademecum/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Félix de Augusta: Pismahuile</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/pismahuile/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1922 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/pismahuile/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is a traditional Mapuche story gathered by the capuchin priest Sigifredo de Frauenhäusel in the Panguipulli area of Chile and published by his collaborator, Félix de Augusta. The informant is Domingo Segundo Huenuñamco of the same parish, who claims that the story is originally from Argentina.
The tale follows the fortunes of Pishmahuile, an extrordinary player of chueca or palin, the most popular Mapuche sport (similar to field hockey).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manuel Manquilef: Comentarios del Pueblo Araucano II</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/manquilef2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1914 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/manquilef2/</guid>
      <description>Subtitle: Jimnasia Nacional (Juegos, Ejercicios y Bailes)
NOT Transcribed
PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manuel Manquilef: A la Raza Araucana (Lillo, ms)</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/manquileflillo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1913 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/manquileflillo/</guid>
      <description>Preliminary transcription by Benjamin Molineaux.
PDF Text (Image Scans) TXT Text (Mapudungun) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomás Guevara: Las Últimas Familias</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/guevarafamilias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1913 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/guevarafamilias/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is a collection of family histories compiled by Tomás Guevara: &amp;ldquo;Las últimas familias i costumbres araucanas&amp;rdquo;, written in collaboration with a number of mapuche consultants, most important of which was probably Manuel Manquilef, who also published ethnographic work independently.
Tagged Text (Web) PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alejandro Cañas: Estudios en Veliche</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/canas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1911 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/canas/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manuel Manquilef: Comentarios del Pueblo Araucano (I)</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/manquilefcomentarios/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1911 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/manquilefcomentarios/</guid>
      <description>Subtitle: (La Faz Social)
Transcribed
Manuel Manquilef (1882&amp;ndash;1950) was a Mapuche teacher, author and intellectual from the turn of the 20th century. Born in the province of Cautín, he attended the main highschool in Temuco, where he met Tomás de Guevara, who he collaborated with on his principal ethnographic works on the Mapuche. Indeed, it is possible that Guevara took much of Manquilef&amp;rsquo;s work and published it under his own name.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomás Guevara: Folklore Araucano</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/guevarafolklore/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1911 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/guevarafolklore/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
At the time of publication (1911), Tomás de Guevara was head teacher at Temuco&amp;rsquo;s main secondary school (Liceo de Temuco). He had long had an interest in Mapuche folklore and ethnography, as many of his students came from the fairly new reservations (reducciones) established in the late 19th century. As with his later texts, much of the compilation and translation of material was actually the work of his collaborator, Manuel Manquilef, a native speaker of Mapudungun and one of the first Mapuche teachers at the school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Félix de Augusta: Lecturas Araucanas</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/augustalecturas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 1910 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/augustalecturas/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is one of the most substantial, careful collections of fairly naturalistic Mapudungun from the turn of the century. It was compiled by Fr. Félix de Augusta and Fr. Sigifredo de Fraunhaeusl, both Bavarian Capuchin priests. For the most part, the texts are on Mapuche-specific topics and have named informants, who were well known by the missionaries. The texts collected by Augusta are mostly from the Lafkenche region near Lake Budi, while the texts collected by Fraunhaeusl are from the Panguipulli area, both broadly within the Central Mapudungun dialect continuum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Félix de Augusta: Gramática Araucana</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/augustagramatica/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1903 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/augustagramatica/</guid>
      <description>Partially Transcribed
The last and most complete of the missionary grammars of Mapudungun is that of the Bavarian Felix José de Augusta. Born in the city of Augsburg in 1860 as August Stephan Kathan, he studied medicine in Würzburg and then in Munich, where he obtained his doctorate. In 1887 he was accepted into the Capuchin order in Laufen, taking the name of Felix Joseph which was followed up by the name of his place of origin: von Augsburg.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Félix de Augusta: Nidolke dəŋu Dios ñi Nùtram</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/augustadios/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1903 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/augustadios/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This translation was produced by Fr. Félix de Augusta for Mapuche children in the Catholic Schools which were run by the Capuchin order in Chile. It is a version of &amp;ldquo;Compendio de la Historia Sagrada&amp;rdquo; (a compendium of sacred history) by Dr. D. Federich Knecht, Archbishop of Freiburg. The translation is a version of the Spanish text edited by D. Vicente Ortí y Escolano.
Spelling, according to Augusta&amp;rsquo;s introduction, follows Rudolf Lenz&amp;rsquo;s principles for the language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rudolf Lenz (ed): Manual de Piedad</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/manualpiedad/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1899 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/manualpiedad/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Raoul de La Grasserie: Grammaire Langue Auca</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/grasserie/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 1898 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/grasserie/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rudolf Lenz: Estudios Araucanos</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/lenzestudios/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 1897 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/lenzestudios/</guid>
      <description>Partially Transcribed
A collection of late-19th-century texts compiled by the German-born linguist Dr. Rudlof Lenz in different regions of Chile. These constitute some of the first real samples of authentic Mapuche speech, as earlier texts were mostly religious prose translated into Mapudungun by Jesuit missionaries. Lenz&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Estudios&amp;rdquo; are also important as they survey a number of different dialects and provide early, fairly-detailed phonetic transcriptions, using state-of-the-art notation techniques for the period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Federico Barbará: Manual o vocabulario de la lengua pampa</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/barbara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 1878 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/barbara/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is a brief grammar and Spanish-Mapudungun vocabulary focusing on the dialect of the pampas, east of the Andes (Puelmapu), written by Liutenant Colonel Carlos Federico Barbará, of the Argentinian army. The grammatical content follows Febrés (1765) quite closely.
A version of the Vocabulary can be found at the following website: https://pueblosoriginarios.com/lenguas/pampa.php UN-Tagged Text (Web) PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guillermo Cox: Viaje a la Patagonia</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/cox/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1863 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/cox/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
Relevant from p.242
PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antonio Hernández Calzada: Confesionario</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/hernandez/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1843 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/hernandez/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serviliano Orbanel: Doctrina Cristiana</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/orbanel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1778 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/orbanel/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bernhard Havestadt: Chilidúģu</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/havestadt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1777 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/havestadt/</guid>
      <description>Partially Transcribed
Fr. Bernhard Havestadt (1714-1778), a German Jesuit, was the author of one of the two 18th century grammars of Mapudungun. A native of Köln, he left the Westphalia monastery of Horst-Maria for the ‘Indies’ in 1746, taking up his post in the region of La Frontera in March of 1748. Here he remained for twenty-two years, leaving a lively record of his evangelisation work and travels.
His grammar,though apparently available in a Spanish-language manuscript in the mid-1750’s, was published &amp;mdash; in Latin &amp;mdash; only in 1777 as Chilidúģu: Sive Tratcatus Linguæ Chilensis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thomas Falkner: A description of Patagonia</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/falkner/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 1774 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/falkner/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
See pages 132-150, on Language.
PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Andrés Febres: Arte de la Lengua General del Reyno de Chile</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/febres/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1764 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/febres/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This was the most widely used early work on Mapudungun. So much so that the HMS Beagle, in its famous travels with Captiain Fitz Roy and young Charles Darwin, carried a copy of it in 1831-6.
Its author was the Catalan Jesuit Andrés Febrés (1732-1790), who arrived to the Mapuche-speaking territories in 1759 at the age of 27. He appears to have learnt the language and written his grammar less than five years after his arrival in Chile.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elias Herckmans: Vocabula Chilensia</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/herckmans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1643 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/herckmans/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is a vocabulary of some 515 words and phrases compiled by Dutch explorers and military men on a reconnaissance mission to Chile from their territories in Brazil. The expedition set out in January 1643 with Hendrik Brouwer as its admiral. The vice-admiral was one Elias Herckmans, Governor of Parahyba, who, upon Brouwer&amp;rsquo;s death in August 1643, took over the entire expedition. As the most senior officer on the expedition and chief negotiator with the local population, the vocabulary is attributed to him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luis de Valdivia: Sermon en Lengua de Chile</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/valdiviasermones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 1621 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/valdiviasermones/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This set of early seventeenth-century sermons was composed by Fr. Luis de Valdiva (1560–1621) , one of the first Spanish Jesuits assigned to Chile. Valdivia played a cruical role in the development of Spanish Crown&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;defensive war&amp;rsquo; policy towards the Mapuche, which suspended direct attacks on native groups and emphasised acculturation.
The sermons are intended as a programatic introduction to Christian faith, with the express intent of converting the Mapuche and having them renounce their traditional beliefs and religious practices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luis de Valdivia: Arte y Gramática</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/valdiviagramatica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1606 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/valdiviagramatica/</guid>
      <description>Partially Transcribed
This is the oldest textual source explicitly focusing on Mapudungun. Its author is Father Luis de Valdivia, a Spanish priest who was one of the original members of the Chilean Mission of the Society of Jesus (Jesuits), founded in 1593.
Throughout his stay in the country, Valdivia was actively involved not only in the education of the colonists and evangelisation of the Mapuche, but also in early attempts to prevent military confrontations between the two groups.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
