<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>HTML disponible on Fuentes para el Corpus Histórico del Mapudungun (CHM)</title>
    <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/tags/html-disponible/</link>
    <description>Recent content in HTML disponible on Fuentes para el Corpus Histórico del Mapudungun (CHM)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>sp</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2021 Benjamín Molineaux</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1930 16:45:54 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/tags/html-disponible/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ernesto Wilhelm de Moesbach: Pascual Coña</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/pc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1930 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/pc/</guid>
      <description>Transcrito
Prólogo, edición y notas de Rodolfo Lenz
Título completo: &amp;ldquo;Vida y costumbres de los indígenas araucanos de la segunda mitad del Siglo XIX&amp;rdquo;
Antecedentes
Este texto es la autobiografía del lonko Pascual Coña, tal como fue relatado al scerdote capuchino Ernst Wilhelm Moesbach.
Un-Tagged Text (Web) PDF Text (Image Scans) TXT Text (Mapudungun) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomás Guevara: Las Últimas Familias</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafamilias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1913 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafamilias/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is a collection of family histories compiled by Tomás Guevara: &amp;ldquo;Las últimas familias i costumbres araucanas&amp;rdquo;, written in collaboration with a number of mapuche informants, most important of which was probably Manuel Manquilef, who also published ethnographic work independently.
Tagged Text (Web) PDF Text (Image Scans) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomás Guevara: Folklore Araucano</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafolklore/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1911 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafolklore/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
At the time of publication (1911), Tomás de Guevara was head teacher at Temuco&amp;rsquo;s main secondary school (Liceo de Temuco). He had long had an interest in Mapuche folklore and ethnography, as many of his students came from the fairly new reservations (reducciones) established in the late 19th century. As with his later texts, much of the compilation and translation of material was actually the work of his collaborator, Manuel Manquilef, a native speaker of Mapudungun and one of the first Mapuche teachers at the school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luis de Valdivia: Sermon en Lengua de Chile</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/valdiviasermones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 1621 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/valdiviasermones/</guid>
      <description>Transcrito
Esta serie de sermones es el primer texto de larga duración escrito en (o traducido al) mapudungun. Los &amp;ldquo;Sermones&amp;rdquo; fueron copuestos por el padre Luys de Valdivia (1560-1621), uno de los primeros jesuitas españoles asignados a la misión de Chile. Valdivia no solo jugó un rol en la descripción de la lengua (véase su Gramática de 1606) y la envangelización del pueblo mapuche, sino que también fue instrumental en el desarrollo de la llamada &amp;lsquo;guerra defensiva&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
