<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academic Study on Source material for the Corpus of Historical Mapudungun (CHM)</title>
    <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/tags/academic-study/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Academic Study on Source material for the Corpus of Historical Mapudungun (CHM)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2021 Benjamín Molineaux</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1930 16:45:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/tags/academic-study/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Ernesto Wilhelm de Moesbach: Pascual Coña</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/pc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1930 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/pc/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
Prologue, editing and notes by Dr. Rudolf Lenz
Full title: &amp;ldquo;Vida y costumbres de los indígenas araucanos de la segunda mitad del Siglo XIX&amp;rdquo;
Background
The text is the autobiography of Pascual Coña, as related to the Capuchin priest Ernst Wilhelm Moesbach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Félix de Augusta: Pismahuile</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/pismahuile/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1922 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/pismahuile/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is a traditional Mapuche story gathered by the capuchin priest Sigifredo de Frauenhäusel in the Panguipulli area of Chile and published by his collaborator, Félix de Augusta. The informant is Domingo Segundo Huenuñamco of the same parish, who claims that the story is originally from Argentina.
The tale follows the fortunes of Pishmahuile, an extrordinary player of chueca or palin, the most popular Mapuche sport (similar to field hockey).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manuel Manquilef: Comentarios del Pueblo Araucano II</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/bonus-texts/manquilef2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1914 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/bonus-texts/manquilef2/</guid>
      <description>Subtitle: Jimnasia Nacional (Juegos, Ejercicios y Bailes)
NOT Transcribed</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomás Guevara: Las Últimas Familias</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/guevarafamilias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1913 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/guevarafamilias/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is a collection of family histories compiled by Tomás Guevara: &amp;ldquo;Las últimas familias i costumbres araucanas&amp;rdquo;, written in collaboration with a number of mapuche informants, most important of which was probably Manuel Manquilef, who also published ethnographic work independently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alejandro Cañas: Estudios en Veliche</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/bonus-texts/canas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1911 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/bonus-texts/canas/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manuel Manquilef: Comentarios del Pueblo Araucano</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/manquilefcomentarios/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1911 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/manquilefcomentarios/</guid>
      <description>Subtitle: (La Faz Social)
Transcribed
Manuel Manquilef (1882&amp;ndash;1950) was a Mapuche teacher, author and intellectual from the turn of the 20th century. Born in the province of Cautín, he attended the main highschool in Temuco, where he met Tomás de Guevara, who he collaborated with on his principal ethnographic works on the Mapuche. Indeed, it is possible that Guevara took much of Manquilef&amp;rsquo;s work and published it under his own name.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomás Guevara: Folklore Araucano</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/guevarafolklore/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1911 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/guevarafolklore/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
At the time of publication (1911), Tomás de Guevara was head teacher at Temuco&amp;rsquo;s main secondary school (Liceo de Temuco). He had long had an interest in Mapuche folklore and ethnography, as many of his students came from the fairly new reservations (reducciones) established in the late 19th century. As with his later texts, much of the compilation and translation of material was actually the work of his collaborator, Manuel Manquilef, a native speaker of Mapudungun and one of the first Mapuche teachers at the school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Félix de Augusta: Lecturas Araucanas</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/augustalecturas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 1910 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/augustalecturas/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is one of the most substantial, careful collections of fairly naturalistic Mapudungun from the turn of the century. It was compiled by Fr. Félix de Augusta and Fr. Sigifredo de Fraunhaeusl, both Bavarian Capuchin priests. For the most part, the texts are on Mapuche-specific topics and have named informants, who were well known by the missionaries. The texts collected by Augusta are mostly from the Lafkenche region near Lake Budi, while the texts collected by Fraunhaeusl are from the Panguipulli area, both broadly within the Central Mapudungun dialect continuum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rudolf Lenz: Estudios Araucanos</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/lenzestudios/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 1897 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/lenzestudios/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
A collection of late-19th-century texts compiled by the German-born linguist Dr. Rudlof Lenz in different regions of Chile. These constitute some of the first real samples of authentic Mapuche speech, as earlier texts were mostly religious prose translated into Mapudungun by Jesuit missionaries. Lenz&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Estudios&amp;rdquo; are also important as they survey a number of different dialects and provide early, fairly-detailed phonetic transcriptions, using state-of-the-art notation techniques for the period.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>