<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Html Available on Fuentes para el Corpus Histórico del Mapudungun (CHM)</title>
    <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/tags/html-available/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Html Available on Fuentes para el Corpus Histórico del Mapudungun (CHM)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>sp</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2021 Benjamín Molineaux</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1913 16:45:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/tags/html-available/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomás Guevara: Las Últimas Familias</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafamilias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1913 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafamilias/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is a collection of family histories compiled by Tomás Guevara: &amp;ldquo;Las últimas familias i costumbres araucanas&amp;rdquo;, written in collaboration with a number of mapuche informants, most important of which was probably Manuel Manquilef, who also published ethnographic work independently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomás Guevara: Folklore Araucano</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafolklore/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1911 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafolklore/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
At the time of publication (1911), Tomás de Guevara was head teacher at Temuco&amp;rsquo;s main secondary school (Liceo de Temuco). He had long had an interest in Mapuche folklore and ethnography, as many of his students came from the fairly new reservations (reducciones) established in the late 19th century. As with his later texts, much of the compilation and translation of material was actually the work of his collaborator, Manuel Manquilef, a native speaker of Mapudungun and one of the first Mapuche teachers at the school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Félix de Augusta: Lecturas Araucanas</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/augustalecturas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 1910 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/augustalecturas/</guid>
      <description>Transcrito
Esta es una de las colecciones más sustanciales y cuidadosas de materiales en mapudungun de principios del Siglo XX. Fue compilado por los Padres Félix de Augusta y Sigifredo de Fraunhäusl, ambos sacerdotes capuchinos bávaros. Por lo general, los textos son de carácter tradicional, tratando temas mapuche y dándo los nombres de cada informante, que eran conocidos de los misioneros.
Los textos recopilados por Augusta son principalmente del área Lafkenche, cerca del Lago Budi, mientras que los textos recopilados por Fraunhäusl son del área de Panguipulli, ambas dentro del la zona del mapudungun central.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Félix de Augusta: Gramática Araucana</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/augustagramatica/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1903 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/augustagramatica/</guid>
      <description>Partially Transcribed
The last and most complete of the missionary grammars of Mapudungun is that of the Bavarian Felix José de Augusta. Born in the city of Augsburg in 1860 as August Stephan Kathan, he studied medicine in Würzburg and then in Munich, where he obtained his doctorate. In 1887 he was accepted into the Capuchin order in Laufen, taking the name of Felix Joseph which was followed up by the name of his place of origin: von Augsburg.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luis de Valdivia: Sermon en Lengua de Chile</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/valdiviasermones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 1621 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/valdiviasermones/</guid>
      <description>Transcrito
Esta serie de sermones es el primer texto de larga duración escrito en (o traducido al) mapudungun. Los &amp;ldquo;Sermones&amp;rdquo; fueron copuestos por el padre Luys de Valdivia (1560-1621), uno de los primeros jesuitas españoles asignados a la misión de Chile. Valdivia no solo jugó un rol en la descripción de la lengua (véase su Gramática de 1606) y la envangelización del pueblo mapuche, sino que también fue instrumental en el desarrollo de la llamada &amp;lsquo;guerra defensiva&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>