<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Txt Available on Source material for the Corpus of Historical Mapudungun (CHM)</title>
    <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/tags/txt-available/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Txt Available on Source material for the Corpus of Historical Mapudungun (CHM)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2021 Benjamín Molineaux</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1930 16:45:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/tags/txt-available/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Ernesto Wilhelm de Moesbach: Pascual Coña</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/pc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1930 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/pc/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
Prologue, editing and notes by Dr. Rudolf Lenz
Full title: &amp;ldquo;Vida y costumbres de los indígenas araucanos de la segunda mitad del Siglo XIX&amp;rdquo;
Background
The text is the autobiography of Pascual Coña, as related to the Capuchin priest Ernst Wilhelm Moesbach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manuel Manquilef: A la Raza Araucana (Lillo, ms)</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/bonus-texts/manquileflillo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1913 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/bonus-texts/manquileflillo/</guid>
      <description>Preliminary transcription by Benjamin Molineaux.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Andrés Febres: Arte de la Lengua General del Reyno de Chile</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/febres/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1764 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/febres/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This was the most widely used early work on Mapudungun. So much so that the HMS Beagle, in its famous travels with Captiain Fitz Roy and young Charles Darwin, carried a copy of it in 1831-6.
Its author was the Catalan Jesuit Andrés Febrés (1732-1790), who arrived to the Mapuche-speaking territories in 1759 at the age of 27. He appears to have learnt the language and written his grammar less than five years after his arrival in Chile.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luis de Valdivia: Sermon en Lengua de Chile</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/valdiviasermones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 1621 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/core-texts/valdiviasermones/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This set of early seventeenth-century sermons was composed by Fr. Luis de Valdiva (1560–1621) , one of the first Spanish Jesuits assigned to Chile. Valdivia played a cruical role in the development of Spanish Crown&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;defensive war&amp;rsquo; policy towards the Mapuche, which suspended direct attacks on native groups and emphasised acculturation.
The sermons are intended as a programatic introduction to Christian faith, with the express intent of converting the Mapuche and having them renounce their traditional beliefs and religious practices.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>