<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Txt Available on Fuentes para el Corpus Histórico del Mapudungun (CHM)</title>
    <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/tags/txt-available/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Txt Available on Fuentes para el Corpus Histórico del Mapudungun (CHM)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>sp</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2021 Benjamín Molineaux</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1913 16:45:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/tags/txt-available/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Manuel Manquilef: A la Raza Araucana (Lillo, ms)</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-adicionales/manquileflillo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1913 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-adicionales/manquileflillo/</guid>
      <description>Preliminary transcription by Benjamin Molineaux.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Andrés Febres: Arte de la Lengua General del Reyno de Chile</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/febres/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1764 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/febres/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This was the most widely used early work on Mapudungun. So much so that the HMS Beagle, in its famous travels with Captiain Fitz Roy and young Charles Darwing, carried a copy of it in 1831-6.
Its author was the Catalan Jesuit Andrés Febrés (1732-1790), who arrived to the Mapuche-speaking territories in 1759 at the age of 27. He appears to have learnt the language and written his grammar less than five years after his arrival in Chile.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luis de Valdivia: Sermon en Lengua de Chile</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/valdiviasermones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 1621 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/valdiviasermones/</guid>
      <description>Transcrito
Esta serie de sermones es el primer texto de larga duración escrito en (o traducido al) mapudungun. Los &amp;ldquo;Sermones&amp;rdquo; fueron copuestos por el padre Luys de Valdivia (1560-1621), uno de los primeros jesuitas españoles asignados a la misión de Chile. Valdivia no solo jugó un rol en la descripción de la lengua (véase su Gramática de 1606) y la envangelización del pueblo mapuche, sino que también fue instrumental en el desarrollo de la llamada &amp;lsquo;guerra defensiva&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>