<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ethnographic Material on Fuentes para el Corpus Histórico del Mapudungun (CHM)</title>
    <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/tags/ethnographic-material/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ethnographic Material on Fuentes para el Corpus Histórico del Mapudungun (CHM)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>sp</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2021 Benjamín Molineaux</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1914 16:45:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/tags/ethnographic-material/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Manuel Manquilef: Comentarios del Pueblo Araucano II</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-adicionales/manquilef2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1914 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-adicionales/manquilef2/</guid>
      <description>Subtitle: Jimnasia Nacional (Juegos, Ejercicios y Bailes)
NOT Transcribed</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomás Guevara: Las Últimas Familias</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafamilias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 1913 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafamilias/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is a collection of family histories compiled by Tomás Guevara: &amp;ldquo;Las últimas familias i costumbres araucanas&amp;rdquo;, written in collaboration with a number of mapuche informants, most important of which was probably Manuel Manquilef, who also published ethnographic work independently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manuel Manquilef: Comentarios del Pueblo Araucano</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/manquilefcomentarios/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1911 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/manquilefcomentarios/</guid>
      <description>Subtitle: (La Faz Social)
Transcribed
Manuel Manquilef (1882&amp;ndash;1950) was a Mapuche teacher, author and intellectual from the turn of the 20th century. Born in the province of Cautín, he attended the main highschool in Temuco, where he met Tomás de Guevara, who he collaborated with on his principal ethnographic works on the Mapuche. Indeed, it is possible that Guevara took much of Manquilef&amp;rsquo;s work and published it under his own name.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomás Guevara: Folklore Araucano</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafolklore/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1911 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/guevarafolklore/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
At the time of publication (1911), Tomás de Guevara was head teacher at Temuco&amp;rsquo;s main secondary school (Liceo de Temuco). He had long had an interest in Mapuche folklore and ethnography, as many of his students came from the fairly new reservations (reducciones) established in the late 19th century. As with his later texts, much of the compilation and translation of material was actually the work of his collaborator, Manuel Manquilef, a native speaker of Mapudungun and one of the first Mapuche teachers at the school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Félix de Augusta: Lecturas Araucanas</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/augustalecturas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 1910 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/augustalecturas/</guid>
      <description>Transcrito
Esta es una de las colecciones más sustanciales y cuidadosas de materiales en mapudungun de principios del Siglo XX. Fue compilado por los Padres Félix de Augusta y Sigifredo de Fraunhäusl, ambos sacerdotes capuchinos bávaros. Por lo general, los textos son de carácter tradicional, tratando temas mapuche y dándo los nombres de cada informante, que eran conocidos de los misioneros.
Los textos recopilados por Augusta son principalmente del área Lafkenche, cerca del Lago Budi, mientras que los textos recopilados por Fraunhäusl son del área de Panguipulli, ambas dentro del la zona del mapudungun central.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rudolf Lenz: Estudios Araucanos</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/lenzestudios/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 1897 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/lenzestudios/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
A collection of late-19th-century texts compiled by the German-born linguist Dr. Rudlof Lenz in different regions of Chile. These constitute some of the first real samples of authentic Mapuche speech, as earlier texts were mostly religious prose translated into Mapudungun by Jesuit missionaries. Lenz&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Estudios&amp;rdquo; are also important as they survey a number of different dialects and provide early, fairly-detailed phonetic transcriptions, using state-of-the-art notation techniques for the period.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>