<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wordlist on Fuentes para el Corpus Histórico del Mapudungun (CHM)</title>
    <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/tags/wordlist/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wordlist on Fuentes para el Corpus Histórico del Mapudungun (CHM)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>sp</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2021 Benjamín Molineaux</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Feb 1878 16:45:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/tags/wordlist/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Federico Barbará: Manual o vocabulario de la lengua pampa</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-adicionales/barbara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 1878 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-adicionales/barbara/</guid>
      <description>NOT Transcribed
This is a brief grammar and Spanish-Mapudungun vocabulary focusing on the dialect of the pampas, east of the Andes (Puelmapu), written by Liutenant Colonel Carlos Federico Barbará, of the Argentinian army. The grammatical content follows Febrés (1765) quite closely.
A version of the Vocabulary can be found at the following website: https://pueblosoriginarios.com/lenguas/pampa.php</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elias Herckmans: Vocabula Chilensia</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/herckmans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1643 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/herckmans/</guid>
      <description>Transcribed
This is a vocabulary of some 515 words and phrases compiled by Dutch explorers and military men on a reconnaissance mission to Chile from their territories in Brazil. The expedition set out in January 1643 with Hendrik Brower as its admiral. The vice-admiral was one Elias Herckmans, Governor of Parahyba, who, upon Brower&amp;rsquo;s death in August 1643, took over the entire expedition. As the most senior officer on the expedition and chief negotiator with the local population, the vocabulary is attributed to him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luis de Valdivia: Arte y Gramática</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/valdiviagramatica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1606 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/sp/textos-clave/valdiviagramatica/</guid>
      <description>Parcialmente Transcrito
Esta es la fuente textual más temprana con la que contamos para el Mapudungun. Su autor es el padre Luys de Valdivia, uno los miembros fundadores de la Misión Chilena de la Sociedad de Jesús (Jesuitas), fundada en 1593.
Durante su estadía en el &amp;ldquo;Reyno de Chile&amp;rdquo;, Valdiva no sólo se involucró en la la educación de los conquistadores y la evangelización del pueblo mapuche, sino que también participó en los intentos tempranos por prevenir las confrontaciones militares entre ambos grupos.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>